A Guide to the Papers of Everett R. Combs, 1911-1957
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Everett R. Combs, 1911-1957
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9712-i
This collection consists of 300 items (1 Hollinger box and oversize folder).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These additional papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by James E. Combs, Lebanon, Virginia, on April 16, 1996.
Biographical/Historical Information
Everett Randolph Combs, son of John William and Jane Kiser Combs, was a native of Russell County, Virginia, where he was elected as clerk for the Circuit Court 1912-1928. He attended Tazewell College, 1896- 1897, and spent the early part of his career as a school teacher and farmer, 1897-1912. He was married to Miss Rassa Candler (1873-1949) in 1897, and they had eleven children. Combs began his long and fruitful association with Harry Byrd, Sr. and his political organization in 1925 when he managed Byrd's campaign for governor in the 9th district. He remained a prominent Democratic party official his entire life and served as Virginia's representative to the National Democratic Committee from 1940-1948. Combs also served as the State Comptroller, 1928-1938, and as chairman of the State Compensation Board from 1934-1938, and 1942-1950, being relieved of the position by Governor James Hubert Price who was not closely associated with the "Byrd machine." At his death, Combs still occupied the post of State Senate Clerk which he had held since 1940. One of his last appointments was as a member of the Virginia 350th Anniversary Commission which visited England in 1956.
Scope and Content Information
These additional papers of Everett R. Combs (1876-1957), political lieutenant and friend of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., consists ca. 300 items (1 Hollinger box and oversize folder), ca. 1911-1957, including: correspondence, photographs, individual news clippings, five scrapbooks of news clippings, business papers and a ledger, memorabilia, invitations, calling cards, membership cards, some political papers, memorabilia and papers pertaining to the Virginia 350th Anniversary Commission Visit to Europe in 1956, genealogy, and a copy of the will of E.R. Combs (1955). There are a few items pertaining to his daughter and executor, Dorothy Elizabeth (Combs)Spring (1901-), who later married Ernest W. Callenbach.
Among the correspondents are Harry F. Byrd, Sr. (1936 June 12; 1940 November 27; 1945 Mar 29; 1955 Jul 18 - telegram; and n.d.); J. Lindsay Almond, Jr. (1955 Aug 22); Dorothy Spring (1944 Jul 18); and E. Griffith Dodson, Clerk of the House of Delegates ([1952] Jan 18 - telegram).
Political papers include a "Declaration of Policy" by the Democratic Party of Virginia (1948 Jul 2); a List of Members of the Constitutional Convention (1956 Mar 5) and a Senate Joint Resolution (n.d.). The photographs are primarily of Everett R. Combs; Combs and political associates, including Harry F. Byrd, Sr., John Dallace, L. McCarthy Downs, and William M. Tuck; family members; the trip of the Virginia 350th Anniversary Commission to Europe; and one of Franklin D. Roosevelt. Oversize photographs include: Governor Elbert Lee Trinkle, Harry F. Byrd, Sr., and E.R. Combs.
Contents List
- Business Papers of E.R. Combs, 1911-1957
- Correspondence, 1936-1957
- "Declaration of Policy" by the Democratic Party of Virginia, July 2, 1948
- Genealogy of the Combs family
- List of Members of the Consititutional Convention and Senate Joint Resolution, March 5, 1956
- Memorabilia and Invitations, 1936-1957
- Newsclippings, ca. 1950-1957
- Photographs, ca. 1936-1957, 3 folders
- Virginia 350th Anniversary Commission Visit to Europe, 1956, 2 folders
- Will of Everett R. Combs, 1955, Typed copy
- Ledger recording Investments of E.R. Combs, 1950-1956
- Scrapbook of News Clippings belonging to E.R. Combs, 1927-1956, 5 volumes
- Tinted Photograph of an Overlook on [The Blue Ridge Parkway?], ca. 1935 (Oversize Q-13)
- Harry F. Byrd, Sr., Signed Photograph inscribed to Ebbie Combs, July 23, 1947 (Oversize Q-13)
- "What We Think of Senator Byrd's Machine" by Virginius Dabney in The Saturday Evening Post,July 7, 1950 (Oversize Q-13)
- Menu for Chez "Maxim's" ca. 1956 (Oversize Q-13)
- Senate of Virginia Senate Resolution No. 1 regarding the Death of Everett R. Combs, January 8, 1958 (Oversize Q-13)
- Cover of magazine PIC featuring the three Harry F. Byrds on Father's Day (Oversize Q-13)
- Original Pencil Sketch of E.R. Combs by Richard Landrum Maye, Jr. (Oversize Q-13)
- Photograph of a Group posed on the steps of the [Capitol?] (Oversize Q-13)
- Four Photographs of Everett R. Combs (Oversize Q-13)
- Photograph of Governor Elbert Lee Trinkle (Oversize Q-13)
- Photograph of E.R. Combs and [his daughter?] (Oversize Q-13)
- Photograph of Natural Bridge, Virginia (Oversize Q-13)
- Large Photograph of E.R. Combs, Dwight D. Eisenhower, and Winston Churchill, 1946 (Oversize Q-13)
- Portraits of E.R. Combs and Mrs. Rassa Candler Combs, 2 paintings (Oversize Q-13)
- Panoramic Photograph of the Senate of Virginia, February 17, 1948 (Oversize Q-13)